<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<feed version="1.0" updated="2025-10-21T08:28:20.131133">
  <entry>
    <source>ACCC News</source>
    <title>Yamaha's proposed acquisition of Telwater raises competition concerns</title>
    <link>https://www.accc.gov.au/media-release/yamahas-proposed-acquisition-of-telwater-raises-competition-concerns</link>
    <published>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 04:09:40 +0000</published>
    <fullText>Date
9 October 2025
Topics
Mergers and acquisitions
The ACCC has outlined its preliminary competition concerns with Yamaha Motor Australia Pty Ltd’s proposed acquisition of Telwater Pty Ltd in a Statement of Issues published today.
Telwater is the largest manufacturer and supplier of aluminium trailer boats in Australia and has strong brand recognition throughout the recreational marine industry. Market participants have told the ACCC that a Telwater aluminium trailer boat is a very important product for many dealers.
Yamaha is a leading supplier of outboard motors. It faces competition from outboard motor brands such as Mercury and Suzuki.
The ACCC’s preliminary view is that the proposed acquisition is likely to have the effect of substantially lessening competition in the wholesale supply of outboard motors in Australia.
“We are concerned that, following the acquisition, Yamaha would have the ability and incentive to link the wholesale supply of Yamaha outboard motors to Telwater aluminium trailer boats, for example, by requiring dealers of Telwater boats to also become Yamaha outboard motor dealers,” ACCC Commissioner Dr Philip Williams said.
“This acquisition could make it much harder for other outboard motor suppliers to compete effectively with Yamaha, ultimately reducing the choice and competitive offerings available to consumers.”
The ACCC is also concerned that the merged entity could seek to reduce the access to dealers and customers by rival suppliers of trailer boats.
“Linking the wholesale supply of Yamaha outboard motors with Telwater aluminium trailer boats could limit how effectively existing and future rival wholesale suppliers of aluminium boats and outboard motors can compete post-merger,” Dr Williams said.
“This could ultimately lead to higher prices and reduced choice or quality for consumers seeking to purchase a new aluminium trailer boat or outboard motor.”
The ACCC invites submissions from interested parties in response to the Statement of Issues by 23 October 2025.
More information, including the Statement of Issues, can be found on the ACCC’s website at
Yamaha Motor Australia Pty Ltd – Telwater Pty Ltd
.
Notes to editors
‘Outboard motors’ are standalone systems that are installed to the outside hull of the boat, as opposed to inboard motors which are installed inside the boat’s hull and used for larger boats.
Trailer boats are small marine vessels that can be fitted to a trailer for easy transportation and generally range between 2 – 9 metres in length. Trailer boats can be made from various materials, with the most common being aluminium or fibreglass.
Aluminium boats are primarily used for recreational boating in Australia. Aluminium boats are generally lighter, more durable and generally less expensive than fibreglass boats.
Aluminium boats and outboard motors are complementary products, often purchased by consumers together. The complementary nature of these products is highly relevant to the ACCC’s competition assessment.
More information on how the ACCC considers conglomerate effects can be found in section 4 of the
ACCC’s Merger Assessment Guidelines
.
Background
Yamaha is proposing to acquire 100 per cent of the shares of Telwater from Bombardier Recreation Products Inc (BRP), alongside a property in Coomera, Queensland used to manufacture, fit and warehouse aluminium trailer boats.
Trailer boats are generally used for leisure activities, such as fishing and cruising. Recreational trailer boats typically use an outboard motor.
Yamaha Motor Company Ltd (YMC) manufactures outboard motors in Asia, primarily in Japan, and imports them into Australia by its wholly owned subsidiary, Yamaha Motor Australia Pty Ltd (Yamaha). Yamaha supplies the outboard motors to dealers (retailers) Australia wide. Dealers then supply the outboard motors to end-customers.
Yamaha does not manufacture boats in Australia. YMC subsidiaries manufacture trailer boats overseas for various international markets. Yamaha and a related business have supplied a small number of these trailer boats to dealers in Australia, primarily via a third party Australian distributor. Yamaha also owns the trademarks for a small number of aluminium trailer boat and trailer brands, which were previously licensed to a third party manufacturer and are not currently in use. Yamaha does not supply trailers for boats in Australia.
Telwater manufactures aluminium trailer boats and trailers in Australia and supplies them to dealers, who then sell to end customers. Telwater currently supplies three lines of trailer boats: Quintrex, Stacer and Yellowfin branded boats.
Telwater supplies custom-fitted trailers that are sold together with its boats (branded under Telwater), or loose trailers (under the brand name “Move”) that can be used for any trailer boat. Telwater also supplies a limited number of outboard motors to dealers as part of a package with a Telwater boat and also potentially a trailer. Telwater is a non-exclusive distributor of Mercury outboard motors, with Mercury also supplying its outboard motors to dealers itself and via other wholesalers. Telwater also supplies a very small number of Rotax outboard motors (which are manufactured and distributed by BRP), as part of a package with some of its boats.
Release number
114/25
General enquiries
Submit an online enquiry
to ask a question or you can
make a report
to help us understand where there are problems.
Media enquiries
media@accc.gov.au or 1300 138 917. The media team is only able to answer requests and questions from journalists. Please only call this number if you are a journalist.</fullText>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <source>ACCC News</source>
    <title>Luke Woodward appointed ACCC Commissioner</title>
    <link>https://www.accc.gov.au/media-release/luke-woodward-appointed-accc-commissioner</link>
    <published>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 23:32:47 +0000</published>
    <fullText>Date
9 October 2025
ACCC Chair Gina Cass-Gottlieb has welcomed the appointment of Luke Woodward as a Commissioner for a 5-year term at the ACCC, commencing from 10 October 2025.
Mr Woodward is regarded as one of Australia’s leading competition and consumer law practitioners. He has more than 30 years of experience spanning competition and consumer matters, mergers and acquisitions, and infrastructure regulation in a range of sectors.
Mr Woodward worked at the ACCC between 1993 and 2000 in roles including executive general manager, general counsel and senior assistant commissioner.
He was most recently a competition and regulation partner and national head of competition law at King and Wood Mallesons.
“I am delighted to welcome Luke back to the ACCC. His expertise and experience across a wide range of fields relevant to the work of the ACCC is recognised not only in Australia but globally,” ACCC Chair Gina Cass-Gottlieb said.
“Luke’s strong litigation experience will be an asset to the ACCC’s work, particularly in our enforcement program and in Australia’s new merger regime.”
Mr Woodward holds a Master of Public Administration from Harvard Kennedy School and degrees in economics and law from the University of Sydney.
He fills a position left vacant after the departure of former ACCC Commissioner Liza Carver.
Further information about the ACCC’s Chair, Deputy Chair and Commissioners is available at
ACCC Chair &amp; Commissioners
.
Release number
113/25
General enquiries
Submit an online enquiry
to ask a question or you can
make a report
to help us understand where there are problems.
Media enquiries
media@accc.gov.au or 1300 138 917. The media team is only able to answer requests and questions from journalists. Please only call this number if you are a journalist.</fullText>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <source>ACCC News</source>
    <title>Elders' acquisition of Delta Agribusiness not opposed, subject to divestments</title>
    <link>https://www.accc.gov.au/media-release/elders-acquisition-of-delta-agribusiness-not-opposed-subject-to-divestments</link>
    <published>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 22:11:43 +0000</published>
    <fullText>Date
9 October 2025
Topics
Mergers and acquisitions
Agriculture
The ACCC will not oppose Elders Limited’s (ASX: ELD) proposed acquisition of Delta Agribusiness after accepting a court-enforceable undertaking that commits Elders to divest six Delta stores in Western Australia.
Elders and Delta both supply rural merchandise such as agricultural chemicals, seed, fertiliser, animal health products and related services, such as agronomy services, through their retail networks. Both companies also supply rural merchandise at the wholesale level.
“Our review closely considered the likely effect of the proposed acquisition on competition in each local area where both Elders and Delta have a retail store, taking into account the specifics of each local area,” ACCC Deputy Chair Mick Keogh said.
&quot;We examined the strength of competing retailers, the particular geographic features and size and type of farms, among other factors. We also engaged with a range of stakeholders including farmers, competing retailers, wholesale suppliers, buying groups and industry bodies as part of our review.&quot;
“The nature of competition in the retail supply of rural merchandise is more localised than is the case in other retail sectors, partly due to the differences in farming in different local areas, and the importance of local relationships,” Mr Keogh said.
“Following an in-depth review, we were concerned that the proposed acquisition would be likely to substantially lessen competition in several local areas in Western Australia.”
To address these concerns, Elders has undertaken to divest six Delta stores in Western Australia, and the ACCC has accepted their undertaking.
The ACCC considered, and has approved, Independent Rural Pty Ltd as the purchaser for Delta stores in Dalwallinu and Kalannie, and E. E. Muir &amp; Sons Pty Limited (Muirs) as the purchaser for Delta stores in Albany, Hyden, Manypeaks and Wellstead.
“The ACCC considers that the undertaking provided by Elders addresses the competition concerns that would otherwise arise from the proposed acquisition. Independent Rural’s and Muirs’ acquisition of Delta stores in each of these local areas will create a strong, independent and viable long-term competitor to Elders in those six areas,” Mr Keogh said.
The ACCC concluded that the proposed acquisition is unlikely to substantially lessen competition in the retail supply of rural merchandise in other local areas where both Elders and Delta own retail stores.
In its
Statement of Issues
, the ACCC also identified potential competition concerns in the retail supply of rural merchandise at a broader regional, state or national level, and in the wholesale supply of rural merchandise in Western Australia.
Having reviewed additional information and engaged in further market inquiries, the ACCC considers that the proposed acquisition is unlikely to substantially lessen competition in the retail supply of rural merchandise at a broader regional, state or national level, or in the wholesale supply of rural merchandise in Western Australia.
“Ultimately, the ACCC did not consider that the proposed acquisition was likely to substantially lessen competition in any relevant market with the undertaking provided by Elders,” Mr Keogh said.
Further information, including the undertaking accepted by the ACCC, can be found on the ACCC’s public register at
Elders Limited – Delta Agribusiness
.
Notes to Editors
‘Agronomy services’ refer to advice provided to farmers by qualified individuals known as agronomists with specialised knowledge in soil and plant sciences. It encompasses a range of advice and services aimed at optimising crop production and farm management.
Rural merchandise is an umbrella term for agricultural products purchased by farmers as inputs into operating a farm and includes agricultural chemicals, seed, fertiliser, animal health products and other miscellaneous merchandise. Some rural merchandise stores also offer agronomic advice.
Background
Elders is an Australian agribusiness. It supplies rural merchandise through its 245 Elders-owned retail stores across the country and also supplies independent stores via its national wholesale business, Australian Independent Rural Retailers (AIRR). Elders also provides agronomic services, livestock and wool agency, real estate, financial, and feed and processing services across Australia.
Delta is an Australian retail supplier of a range of rural merchandise products and related services. Delta operates 64 retail stores, primarily in regional areas of New South Wales, Victoria, South Australia and Western Australia, and also operates a wholesale business (Delta WA) in Western Australia. Delta also provides agronomic services, livestock agency, grain marketing, real estate and financial services.
Release number
112/25
General enquiries
Submit an online enquiry
to ask a question or you can
make a report
to help us understand where there are problems.
Media enquiries
media@accc.gov.au or 1300 138 917. The media team is only able to answer requests and questions from journalists. Please only call this number if you are a journalist.</fullText>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <source>ACCC News</source>
    <title>Telstra fined $18 million for misleading Belong customers over broadband speed claims</title>
    <link>https://www.accc.gov.au/media-release/telstra-fined-18-million-for-misleading-belong-customers-over-broadband-speed-claims</link>
    <published>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 23:22:11 +0000</published>
    <fullText>Date
3 October 2025
Topics
Compliance and enforcement
Scam warning:
The ACCC is aware that scammers may call, email or text to falsely offer to help get compensation from various businesses. They may use this media release about compensation to convince people their contact is real.
STOP
– Don’t give money or personal information to anyone if you’re unsure. Scammers will create a sense of urgency. Don’t rush to act. Don’t click on links even if the message appears to come from Optus. Say ‘no’, hang up, delete.
CHECK
– Ask yourself could the call, email or text be fake? Scammers pretend to be from organisations and entities you know and trust. Contact the organisation using information you source independently, so that you can verify if it is real or not.
PROTECT
– Act quickly if something feels wrong. Contact your bank immediately if you lose money. If you have provided personal information call IDCARE on 1800 595 160. The more we talk the less power they have. Report scams to the National Anti-Scam Centre’s Scamwatch service at
scamwatch.gov.au
when you see them.
Telstra has been ordered by the Federal Court to pay a penalty of $18 million for breaching the Australian Consumer Law after it moved almost 9,000 Belong customers to a lower speed plan without telling them.
In October and November 2020, Telstra migrated 8,897 customers on its Belong brand NBN plans from their current plan which provided a maximum upload speed of 40 Mbps to a service that provided a maximum upload speed of only 20 Mbps. The download speed was unchanged at 100Mbps.
Telstra did not tell customers of the change in maximum upload speed in their service at the time of the change.
“The $18 million penalty sends a strong message to all businesses that they cannot mislead consumers by making changes to key aspects of a service without informing customers of those changes” ACCC Commissioner Anna Brakey said.
In addition to the penalty, all affected customers have, or will be, remediated by Telstra with a credit or payment of $15 for each month the customer had been on the lower upload speed plan.
The total remediation that Telstra will pay to affected customers exceeds $2.3 million.
“Telstra’s failure to inform customers that their broadband service had been changed denied them the opportunity to decide whether the changed service was suitable for their needs,” Ms Brakey said.
“Misleading pricing and claims in relation to essential services, with a particular focus on telecommunications, is one of ACCC’s current enforcement priorities.”
Telstra made payments to some affected customers prior to the ACCC commencing proceedings. The remaining payments to customers are being made in accordance with a
court-enforceable undertaking
Telstra has given to the ACCC. Those customers will be contacted by Belong via email.
The Court also ordered Telstra to pay a contribution to the ACCC’s costs. The Court will publish its reasons for judgment at a later date.
Telstra co-operated with the ACCC by making joint submissions to the Court about orders, including in relation to penalties.
Background
Belong was launched by Telstra in 2013 as a low-cost mobile and internet service provider, operating semi-independently in a number of areas, including products, marketing, service, billing and parts of IT.
Upload speed refers to the speed an individual’s internet connection can allow data to be sent from their devices to the internet e.g. sending emails, streaming video calls and conferences.
In May 2020, NBN Co launched a series of new wholesale consumer speed tiers, including a new 100/20Mbps wholesale speed tier, which provided a maximum download speed of 100mbps and a maximum upload speed of 20mbps. This speed tier costs retail service providers $7 less per month than the 100/40Mbps plan on a wholesale level.
The ACCC commenced its
court action
against Telstra on 6 December 2022, and the
Federal Court made findings against Telstra
on 21 February 2025.
Release number
111/25
General enquiries
Submit an online enquiry
to ask a question or you can
make a report
to help us understand where there are problems.
Media enquiries
media@accc.gov.au or 1300 138 917. The media team is only able to answer requests and questions from journalists. Please only call this number if you are a journalist.</fullText>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <source>ACCC News</source>
    <title>East coast gas supply outlook eases for first quarter 2026</title>
    <link>https://www.accc.gov.au/media-release/east-coast-gas-supply-outlook-eases-for-first-quarter-2026</link>
    <published>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 02:00:08 +0000</published>
    <fullText>Date
1 October 2025
Topics
Energy
Gas supply on Australia’s east coast is expected to improve in the first quarter of 2026, but the outlook still depends on how much uncontracted gas LNG producers decide to export, according to the
ACCC’s latest gas inquiry report
released today.
The report indicates a gas supply surplus of between 2 and 24 petajoules (PJ) is expected for the east coast, depending on what the LNG producers decide to do with their uncontracted gas.
“The Queensland LNG producers have reported a reduction in contracted LNG exports, and now expect to have 22 PJ of uncontracted gas available in the first quarter of next year,” ACCC Commissioner Anna Brakey said.
“Given ongoing concerns about sufficiency of domestic gas supply, the ACCC will be monitoring whether and how this gas is offered to domestic buyers.”
“Despite the improvement, the supply-demand outlook remains tight in the southern states,” Ms Brakey said.
“For the first time, southern gas producers are not expecting to produce surplus gas in the first quarter of the year, when demand is usually at its lowest. This may create challenges for fully replenishing southern gas storage facilities ahead of winter 2026.”
Regional supply-demand outlook for quarter 1 2026 (PJ)
Source: ACCC analysis of data obtained from gas producers in July 2025 and of the domestic demand forecast (Step Change scenario) from AEMO, Gas Statement of Opportunities (GSOO), March 2025.
Note: Totals may not sum due to rounding. The quantity required to meet long-term LNG SPAs includes feed gas requirements (such as fuel) required to produce LNG. LNG producers' uncontracted gas has been zeroed out when negative as this gas must be acquired from the domestic market, either as additional gas production, purchases or a reduction in exports which would have a net 0 impact on the forecast.
Gas suppliers and users have signed more long-term supply deals so far this year, for supply in 2026 and 2027.
But the report found, despite this, the total amount of gas secured under these contracts remains below levels seen before 2022. Most of the contracts are for only one year.
Prices offered by gas producers for 2026 supply eased in the first half of 2025, falling by an average of 2 per cent to $13.12 per gigajoule (GJ) compared to the second half of 2024. In comparison, prices offered by gas retailers for 2026 supply averaged $14.33/GJ.
For 2027, the average price under producer contracts was $13.93/GJ, while retailer contracts averaged $14.30/GJ. Suppliers contracted a total of 18 PJ of gas for 2026 supply, and 21 PJ for 2027.
Gas policy measures have not made a material difference for local users
The report also reviewed the impact of the Gas Market Code (Gas Code), the Commonwealth Heads of Agreement with LNG exporters (HoA) and the Australian Domestic Gas Security Mechanism (ADGSM), following the ACCC’s initial observations reported in June 2025.
The ACCC has found these measures may have added some gas to the local market, but, overall, they have not materially improved outcomes for gas users.
“There are limits to what the gas policy measures can achieve on their own if the underlying causes of inadequate supply and ineffective competition are not addressed,” Ms Brakey said.
“In addition, they may also be having some unintended incentive effects and causing inefficiencies in gas supply negotiations.”
The ACCC’s review has found that the 2023 reforms to the ADGSM appear to have reduced LNG producers’ incentives to make a net contribution to the domestic market.
These changed incentives appear to have had the unintended consequence of exacerbating the risk of domestic supply shortfalls.
Further, since the 2022 HoA was entered into, the volumes of gas being offered and supplied by the LNG producers to the domestic market have declined over time, while LNG export volumes have increased.
The ACCC’s
submission
to the Gas Market Review outlines the ACCC’s experience and observations arising from the inquiry to inform government consideration of reforms to promote longer-term gas market efficiency and measures to ensure that, in the interim, the Code, ADGSM and HoA are fit for purpose.
Background
In 2017, the Australian Government directed the ACCC to conduct a
wide-ranging inquiry
to improve transparency of the gas market in Australia and support its efficient operation, and to monitor gas supply. On 29 August 2025 a
new direction
was made to formally extend the inquiry to 2030 and to establish quarterly reporting.
The ACCC’s next interim report is scheduled for December 2025
Release number
110/25
General enquiries
Submit an online enquiry
to ask a question or you can
make a report
to help us understand where there are problems.
Media enquiries
media@accc.gov.au or 1300 138 917. The media team is only able to answer requests and questions from journalists. Please only call this number if you are a journalist.</fullText>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <source>ACCC News</source>
    <title>Federal Court orders Optus to pay $100m penalty for unconscionable conduct</title>
    <link>https://www.accc.gov.au/media-release/federal-court-orders-optus-to-pay-100m-penalty-for-unconscionable-conduct</link>
    <published>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 05:04:05 +0000</published>
    <fullText>Date
24 September 2025
Topics
Buying and selling products and services
Compliance and enforcement
Telecommunications and internet
Scam warning:
The ACCC is aware that scammers may call, email or text to falsely offer to help get compensation from various businesses. They may use this media release about compensation to convince people their contact is real.
STOP
– Don’t give money or personal information to anyone if you’re unsure. Scammers will create a sense of urgency. Don’t rush to act. Don’t click on links even if the message appears to come from Optus. Say ‘no’, hang up, delete.
CHECK
– Ask yourself could the call, email or text be fake? Scammers pretend to be from organisations and entities you know and trust. Contact the organisation using information you source independently, so that you can verify if it is real or not.
PROTECT
– Act quickly if something feels wrong. Contact your bank immediately if you lose money. If you have provided personal information call IDCARE on 1800 595 160. The more we talk the less power they have. Report scams to the National Anti-Scam Centre’s Scamwatch service at
scamwatch.gov.au
when you see them.
Optus Mobile Pty Ltd (Optus) has today been ordered by the Federal Court to pay a penalty of $100 million for engaging in unconscionable conduct when selling mobile phones and contracts to hundreds of Australians, and subsequent debt collection in a case brought by the ACCC.
The Court has imposed this penalty after Optus admitted it acted unconscionably, in breach of the Australian Consumer Law, and agreed to make joint submissions with the ACCC to the Court that a total penalty of $100 million was appropriate.
In many instances the affected consumers did not want or need, could not use or could not afford the phones and contracts they were sold and, in some cases, consumers were pursued for debts resulting from these sales.
Many of the affected consumers were vulnerable or experiencing disadvantage, such as living with a mental disability, diminished cognitive capacity or learning difficulties, being financially dependent or unemployed, having limited financial literacy or English not being a first language. Many of the consumers were First Nations Australians from regional, remote and very remote parts of Australia.
“Optus’s conduct in this case was truly appalling, and we welcome the substantial penalty imposed by the Court and the deterrence message that it will send,” ACCC Deputy Chair Catriona Lowe said.
“During the course of our investigation we heard from many people who had not only experienced significant financial harm, but also emotional distress and fear after being pursued by debt collectors for long periods.”
“A company of Optus’s size should have had better systems and controls in place to identify and stop this sort of behaviour,” Ms Lowe said.
In his decision, Justice O’Sullivan said the consequences of Optus’s conduct were “profound”.
“Numerous individuals experienced severe financial harm, emotional distress, and social shame,” he said.
“Particularly damaging was the heightened risk of losing access to essential telecommunications services when faced with inflated service costs.”
In addition to the financial penalty, Optus has also provided the ACCC with a
five-year court-enforceable undertaking
that it will compensate impacted consumers and improve its internal systems.
Optus’s conduct impacted over 400 consumers and occurred at 16 Optus stores between August 2019 and July 2023. Any consumer who considers they may have been impacted by similar conduct should contact Optus.
Examples of the misconduct included:
putting undue pressure on consumers to purchase a large number of products, including expensive phones and accessories, that they did not want or need, could not use or could not afford;
failing to explain relevant terms and conditions to vulnerable consumers in a manner they could understand, resulting in them not understanding their ongoing payment obligations;
not having regard to whether consumers had Optus coverage where they lived;
selling products and services which Optus knew, or ought reasonably to have known, the consumers could not afford; and
misleading these consumers to believe that goods were free or included as part of a bundle at no additional cost.
Many impacted consumers were supported by local advocates, financial counsellors and carers in trying to seek a resolution with Optus.
“We commend the dedicated and hardworking people who assisted many of the affected consumers, and we also thank the Telecommunications Industry Ombudsman for drawing the broader conduct to our attention,” Ms Lowe said.
In the case of Optus’s Mount Isa store, which has now closed, the telco pursued debts in circumstances where its then senior management knew that those debts related to contracts for goods and services that appeared to have been entered into at the Optus Mount Isa Store fraudulently and without consumer knowledge.
Optus’s then senior management became increasingly aware that Optus staff were engaging in the inappropriate sales practices and that Optus’s systems and controls could not stop the conduct. Optus acknowledged it failed to promptly take steps to fix deficiencies in its systems, which allowed the conduct to continue.
Commission-based sales arrangements for Optus’s sales staff had the clear potential to incentivise the inappropriate sales conduct, despite the Telecommunications Consumer Protections Code requiring Optus, from 17 June 2022, to have regard to the
ACCC’s best practice recommendations
which recommend businesses avoid commission-based selling because of its potential to exacerbate the vulnerability of consumers.
This case follows similar ACCC action against Telstra, which was ordered in
May 2021
to pay a $50 million penalty for engaging in unconscionable conduct when it sold mobile contracts to 108 First Nations Australians consumers between at least 1 January 2016 and about 27 August 2018.
Examples of the alleged conduct
A First Nations consumer visited an Optus store in a metro area. They were sold multiple Optus mobile plans and services, including two mobile phones, as well as accessories. The Optus sales representative manipulated the credit check, which enabled them to sell the consumer Optus services and products that they could not afford. Despite the details of the sale coming to the attention of Optus’s fraud team, the consumer’s debt in excess of $3,000 was referred to an external debt collection agency. The debt continued to be pursued by Optus for over a year.
In a separate example, Optus entered into four contracts with a consumer who lived with deafness and communicated by Australian Sign Language. Optus staff failed to explain the terms of the consumer’s contract in a manner which they could understand. The consumer was on a disability pension, and the cost of the contracts was more than they could afford. In addition, the consumer did not need and could not use the Optus products and services. It was only with significant time and assistance of the consumer’s support worker that the consumer was able to cancel the contracts.
In 2019, an internal Optus investigation into customer accounts at the Optus store in Mount Isa resulted in a report that stated that the store manager had falsified identification documents and consumer information to create contracts for services, and had used the identities of First Nations consumers who were not aware that their identities had been used. Another report identified 82 contracts that appeared to have been fraudulently completed without consumer knowledge.
After Optus was notified of the conduct that was the subject of the reports, including its senior management at the time, it still referred and sold outstanding debts associated with some of those contracts to third party debt collection and factoring agencies. Some consumers whose identities were associated with the relevant customer accounts were subject to threats of legal proceedings being commenced against them and of reporting defaults to credit reporting bodies. Some customers continued to be pursued by third party collections agencies until as late as July 2024 and Optus had not taken steps to stop that occurring.
The ACCC acknowledges Optus’s cooperation in resolving the Court proceedings at an early stage and providing a court-enforceable undertaking. The undertaking includes:
a 3-year consumer remediation program
changes to remuneration and incentives for Optus sales staff designed to prevent further conduct from occurring
a requirement for Optus to ensure that certain Optus Licensee stores in the Northern Territory, regional Queensland and South Australia are directly operated by Optus
process and system changes, for example improvements to Optus’s complaints handling process for consumers experiencing vulnerability and/or disadvantage, and
a $1 million donation to an organisation facilitating digital literacy of First Nations Australians.
The Court also ordered Optus to pay a contribution to the ACCC’s costs, by consent.
Optus customer support
Consumers who think they may have been impacted by conduct similar to that
outlined in Optus’s undertaking
to the ACCC can call Optus’s specialist customer care team on 1300 082 820 for further information or support.
They can also visit the
Sales Misconduct Response page
on Optus’s website.
Background
Questions regarding the recent Optus outage affecting triple-0 call services are unrelated to this judgment and should be directed to the
Australian Communications and Media Authority
(ACMA). The ACCC does not have a role in regulating or enforcing compliance with emergency call service regulations and other related rules.
Optus is Australia’s second largest telecommunications provider. It is a wholly-owned subsidiary of Singtel Optus Pty Ltd, a foreign owned private company.
In Australia, Optus’s retail stores are either:
owned and operated directly by Optus RetailCo Pty Ltd; or
owned and operated through third party licensees, through Retail License Agreements. For example, prior to Optus buying back certain stores, all Optus stores in the Adelaide region were owned and operated by Mavaya Pty Ltd, and all Optus stores in the Northern Territory, as well as several in regional Queensland, were owned and operated by Suntel Communications Pty Ltd.
On 31 October 2024, the ACCC commenced
court action against Optus
. The investigation was prompted by a referral from the Telecommunications Industry Ombudsman.
On 18 June 2025, the ACCC announced that
Optus had admitted
to engaging in unconscionable conduct and agreed to a total penalty of $100 million, subject to Court approval.
Release number
109/25
General enquiries
Submit an online enquiry
to ask a question or you can
make a report
to help us understand where there are problems.
Media enquiries
media@accc.gov.au or 1300 138 917. The media team is only able to answer requests and questions from journalists. Please only call this number if you are a journalist.</fullText>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <source>ACCC News</source>
    <title>JustAnswer in Court for alleged misleading prices, subscription trap and government affiliation claims</title>
    <link>https://www.accc.gov.au/media-release/justanswer-in-court-for-alleged-misleading-prices-subscription-trap-and-government-affiliation-claims</link>
    <published>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 22:30:05 +0000</published>
    <fullText>Date
23 September 2025
Topics
Advertising and promotions
Compliance and enforcement
The ACCC has instituted proceedings in the Federal Court against JustAnswer LLC for allegedly misleading consumers as to its affiliation with Australian Ombudsman or Government agencies and the cost of its online question and answer service, in breach of consumer laws.
It is alleged that from about 1 November 2022, JustAnswer made false or misleading representations via a chat widget on its website that consumers could use the online question and answer service for just AUD$2. However, in addition to paying the $2 joining fee, consumers were signed up to an ongoing subscription costing between around $50 and $90 per month.
The ACCC alleges that consumers were not adequately informed of the ongoing subscription fee and suffered financial harm as a result.
“Had consumers been aware that the total price of the JustAnswer online service cost at least 25 times more per month than the promoted joining fee, they may have chosen not to use it,” ACCC Deputy Chair Catriona Lowe said.
“Through its chat widget, JustAnswer offered to connect consumers to ‘experts’ in particular subject areas for a one-off fee of $2. The chat widget didn’t disclose any other charges, and the substantially higher ongoing monthly fee was not mentioned until consumers were directed to a payment screen.”
“The monthly subscription fee was shown in a way that we believe many consumers would not have seen,” Ms Lowe said.
“Manipulative online design practices which guide consumers to sign up for subscriptions they do not want or did not intend to buy can cause distress and financial loss.”
In addition to the alleged price misrepresentations, the ACCC alleges JustAnswer misled consumers by purporting that it or its services were sponsored or approved by, or otherwise affiliated with, the Fair Work Ombudsman, an Australian Ombudsman, or an Australian Government department.
“We consider some consumers may have engaged with JustAnswer on the mistaken belief that their questions would be answered by an independent ombudsman, such as the Fair Work Ombudsman,” Ms Lowe said.
“The ACCC commenced this investigation after receiving large numbers of complaints from consumers who claimed they were not aware of the ongoing subscription charges or who thought they were dealing with an Australian government body.”
The ACCC is seeking compensation orders for affected consumers, injunctions, civil pecuniary penalties, publication orders, and costs, as well as declarations that JustAnswer contravened consumer laws and the implementation of a compliance program.
Background
JustAnswer is registered and based in the United States and operates its business in 196 countries, with more than 700 employees.
It provides a service connecting consumers to subject matter ‘experts’ in areas such as medicine, law, accounting and technology, who are available to answer consumers’ questions. This service can be accessed via
JustAnswer’s website
or its Android/iOS app, the latter of which is not subject to allegations in this proceeding.
Consumers who use a search engine to find information on a particular topic may come across search results with links to JustAnswer’s website. This included search ads sponsored by JustAnswer.
In June, the ACCC published the tenth and final report of its
Digital Platform Services Inquiry
, which found consumers continue to face harms from unfair trading practices including manipulative design operations, such as using interfaces that direct consumers to more expensive subscriptions or purchase options, as well as undisclosed sponsorships and subscription traps. A subscription trap is when a business misleads a consumer into signing up for a subscription by representing that they are making a one-off purchase, or by making cancellation of a subscription difficult.
Consumer issues in the digital economy are one of the ACCC’s current enforcement priorities. This includes work in addressing unfair subscription-related practices, including subscription traps.
Concise Statement
This document contains the ACCC's initiating court document in relation to this matter. We will not be uploading further documents in the event these initial documents are subsequently amended.
ACCC v JustAnswer LLC - Concise Statement
(
PDF 626.58 KB
)
Release number
108/25
General enquiries
Submit an online enquiry
to ask a question or you can
make a report
to help us understand where there are problems.
Media enquiries
media@accc.gov.au or 1300 138 917. The media team is only able to answer requests and questions from journalists. Please only call this number if you are a journalist.</fullText>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <source>ACCC News</source>
    <title>Lower retail petrol prices in the June quarter reflect falls in international prices</title>
    <link>https://www.accc.gov.au/media-release/lower-retail-petrol-prices-in-the-june-quarter-reflect-falls-in-international-prices</link>
    <published>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 01:03:52 +0000</published>
    <fullText>Date
11 September 2025
Topics
Petrol and fuel
Retail petrol prices were lower in all capital cities and on average across regional locations in the June quarter 2025, according to the
ACCC’s latest quarterly petrol monitoring report
.
Quarterly average retail petrol prices across the five largest cities (Sydney, Melbourne, Brisbane, Adelaide and Perth) were 175.7 cents per litre (cpl), a decrease of 6.5 cpl from the previous quarter. Among the five largest cities, prices decreased the most in Brisbane (by 14.4 cpl).
×
Close
Click to enlarge
The decrease in average retail prices mainly reflected lower international prices for refined petrol (largely driven by international crude oil prices). A higher average AUD-USD exchange rate also helped make the cost of international refined petrol relatively less expensive in Australian dollar terms.
Crude oil prices predominantly trended downward in the quarter, as trade tensions impacted financial and commodity markets. Another influence was the Organisation of the Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) and other crude oil producing countries including Russia (together, OPEC+) agreeing to a further unwind of production cuts.
“Crude oil prices jumped in mid-June following impacts from the Israel-Iran conflict, but they settled and decreased toward the end of June,” ACCC Commissioner Brakey said. “The jump in international prices contributed to average retail petrol prices across the five largest cities briefly moving higher in early July, before reducing shortly after.”
The following figure shows the movements in average retail petrol prices across the five largest cities from July 2023 to July 2025.
Seven-day rolling average retail petrol prices across the five largest cities in nominal terms
Source: ACCC calculations based on data from Informed Sources.
Notes: The grey shaded area in the figure represents the June quarter 2025. The blue shaded area in the figure represents July 2025 (the month after the June quarter 2025 ended). A 7-day rolling average price is the average of the current day’s price and prices on the 6 previous days.
Across the five largest cities, seven-day rolling average retail petrol prices increased to 180.6 cpl at the end of the quarter. By the end of July average prices decreased to 168.3 cpl.
Petrol gross indicative retail differences were 16.4 cpl across the five largest cities in the June quarter, an increase of 2.0 cpl from the previous quarter. Gross indicative retail differences are a broad indicator of gross retail margins and include both retail operating costs and retail profits.
Average retail petrol prices were lower in the smaller capital cities and on average across regional locations
In Canberra, Hobart and Darwin, quarterly average retail petrol prices also decreased. Quarterly average retail petrol prices in Canberra decreased the most among the eight capital cities (by 17.0 cpl).
Across more than 190 regional locations that the ACCC monitors, average retail petrol prices (in aggregate) were 179.2 cpl, a decrease of 5.1 cpl from the previous quarter.
“We were pleased to see lower prices across most locations in Australia in the quarter, providing some relief to motorists,” Ms Brakey said.
Retail diesel prices were also lower in all capital cities
Across the five largest cities, quarterly average retail diesel prices were 178.4 cpl, a decrease of 8.5 cpl from the previous quarter.
Quarterly average retail diesel prices decreased in all capital cities. Diesel prices dropped the most in Hobart (by 13.3 cpl), followed by Sydney and Melbourne (by 10.4 cpl).
Retail diesel prices generally follow international diesel benchmark prices, which accounted for the largest component of retail diesel prices.
The ACCC welcomes a fuel price transparency scheme in Victoria
In August 2025, the Victorian Government made new regulations requiring fuel retailers to provide timely fuel price data as soon as practicable, and no more than thirty minutes after a change in price. This follows the government’s announcement of its Fair Fuel Plan earlier in the year. The pricing data is expected to be available to motorists on the Service Victoria app later this year.
“We encourage motorists to shop around for lower fuel prices as there is often a range of prices available,” Ms Brakey said.
“We have long been an advocate of fuel prices transparency schemes. This fuel price reporting and subsequent publishing will give motorists in Victoria access to near real-time fuel price data.”
Victoria is the last jurisdiction in Australia to establish a fuel price transparency scheme.
Annual average retail petrol and diesel prices were lower in the 2024-25 financial year
The ACCC’s latest report also provides results for the 2024-25 financial year. Across the five largest cities, annual average retail petrol prices were 180.1 cpl, a decrease of 15.0 cpl, or around 8 per cent from 2023–24 (195.1 cpl).
Annual average petrol gross indicative retail differences
across the five largest cities were 15.9 cpl, which was the same as the 10-year average, in real (inflation adjusted) terms.
Across the five largest cities, annual average retail diesel prices were 181.9 cpl, a decrease of 18.1 cpl, or around 9 per cent from 2023–24 (200.0 cpl).
The decreases in average retail petrol and diesel prices largely reflected lower international prices for refined petrol and refined diesel.
In each capital city, annual average retail petrol prices in cents per litre, and the change from 2023–24 were:
In each capital city, annual average retail diesel prices in cents per litre, and the change from 2023–24 were:
Release number
107/25
General enquiries
Submit an online enquiry
to ask a question or you can
make a report
to help us understand where there are problems.
Media enquiries
media@accc.gov.au or 1300 138 917. The media team is only able to answer requests and questions from journalists. Please only call this number if you are a journalist.</fullText>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <source>ACCC News</source>
    <title>ACCC will not oppose acquisition of BGC Cementitious after changes to transaction</title>
    <link>https://www.accc.gov.au/media-release/accc-will-not-oppose-acquisition-of-bgc-cementitious-after-changes-to-transaction</link>
    <published>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:10:29 +0000</published>
    <fullText>Date
11 September 2025
Topics
Mergers and acquisitions
The ACCC will not oppose the acquisition of BGC Cementitious (BGC) by Cement Australia, Holcim, Heidelberg Materials Australia (HMA) and Adbri Pty Ltd.
BGC Cementitious and Cement Australia both supply aggregates, ready-mix concrete (RMX), asphalt and cement among other related products and services in greater Perth.
The ACCC decided not to oppose the transaction after the merger parties amended their original proposal.
“An initial proposed structure for the acquisition of BGC by Cement Australia, Holcim and HMA raised significant preliminary competition concerns for us, particularly in relation to the competitive overlap in RMX and aggregate quarries in Western Australia,” ACCC Commissioner Dr Philip Williams said.
After the ACCC expressed concerns about the initial proposal, a new proposed structure was put forward involving the sale of certain assets to Adbri.
Adbri supplies cement in Western Australia but does not supply aggregates, RMX or asphalt in Western Australia.
The amended acquisition involves BGC divesting WA Cementitious, including cement assets and some limited RMX plants to Cement Australia, Holcim and HMA, with Adbri acquiring the majority of BGC’s RMX assets as well as BGC’s aggregates, asphalt, transport and materials technology centre assets.
“We examined the amended acquisition proposal very closely,” Dr Williams said.
“In particular we looked at both the loss of BGC as a competitor in the supply of RMX and the risk that Cement Australia or Adbri would use their position as cement suppliers to hinder the ability of rival RMX suppliers to compete.”
“While we acknowledge strong concerns from some market participants, we found that Cement Australia and Adbri would be likely to compete with each other to supply cement to RMX competitors after the acquisition.” Dr Williams said.
In reaching its view, the ACCC found that Cement Australia and Adbri would have significant excess capacity in the production of cement in Western Australia.
The ACCC also looked closely at the margins the merger parties earn at various levels of the supply chain, and the profit incentives that would likely drive their decisions post-acquisition.
The ACCC also considered the extent to which the acquirers would have market power and be able to increase the price of RMX across Perth as well as in more localised markets.
The ACCC found, based on a detailed data analysis of existing delivery patterns and the marginal cost of servicing customers, that rival suppliers of RMX would continue to constrain HMA and Holcim post-acquisition across Perth.
Ultimately, the ACCC did not find that the amended acquisition would likely substantially lessen competition in any market.
Notes to editors
‘Aggregates’
refer to a particulate material used in construction and includes sand aggregate and crushed hard rock aggregates. Aggregates are quarried and used as an input into RMX and asphalt (as well as for some other mining and construction purposes).
‘Cement
’ refers to a fine soft powder made from limestone, clay and other materials. It is used as the binding ingredient in RMX and hardens after contact with water.
‘
RMX
’ is concrete that is produced in and delivered by truck in a freshly mixed and unhardened state. RMX is manufactured from cement, aggregates, water and other additives.
‘Asphalt
’ is a sticky, black, tar-like substance used to pave roads, parking lots, and other surfaces. It's made from mixing bitumen, aggregates and other filler materials in an asphalt plant.
Background
On 11 February 2025, Cement Australia, Holcim and HMA requested informal merger clearance to acquire BGC’s aggregates, cement, RMX, asphalt, transport and materials technology centre assets in WA.
After the ACCC raised preliminary competition concerns with the Initial Proposed Acquisition, Cement Australia, Holcim, and HMA put forward the Amended Proposed Acquisition in May 2025, with BGC’s support, that incorporates Adbri as a party.
The ACCC’s decision relates to the Amended Proposed Acquisition, pursuant to which:
Adbri will acquire certain BGC assets including aggregates and asphalt sites, six of BGC’s RMX sites, two mobile RMX plants and the transport assets associated with those assets and the company’s Materials Technology Centre (excluding cement-related assets),
Cement Australia, Holcim and HMA will acquire BGC’s cement plant and cement transport assets, and three RMX sites.
BGC Cementitious
is a division of the BGC Group which supplies cementitious products in WA including cement and slag through BGC Cement, aggregate, hard rock and manufactured sand through BGC Quarries (which operates a hard rock quarry at The Lakes), RMX through BGC Concrete, and asphalt through BGC Asphalt. BGC Transport owns and operates vehicles, operating out of different hubs used in the BGC Cementitious business. BGC’s Materials Technology Centre is a testing laboratory for cement, RMX, asphalt and related products located in Hazelmere.
Cement Australia
is a privately held 50:50 joint venture between Holcim and HMA. Cement Australia supplies cementitious products and services, including bulk and packaged cement, fly ash and slag products. Cement Australia has operations in NSW, Victoria, Queensland, SA, ACT, WA and Tasmania. Cement Australia does not have any cement or slag production facilities in WA. The operations of Cement Australia are governed by a Framework Agreement which establishes ring-fencing between Cement Australia, Holcim and HMA, placing restrictions on Holcim and HMA from accessing information about the sale of cementitious products by Cement Australia to each other party to the joint venture or to other customers.
Holcim
is a Swiss multinational company that manufactures and supplies various building materials across Australia, including aggregates, RMX and pre-cast pipes. In WA, Holcim owns and operates several RMX plants and aggregate quarries (hard rock and sand).
HMA
is a German multinational company that manufactures and supplies various building materials across Australia, including aggregates, RMX and asphalt. In WA, HMA owns and operates a number of RMX plants and aggregate quarries (hard rock and sand).
Adbri
is an Australian company which manufactures, imports and supplies various building materials across Australia, including clinker, cement, quicklime, aggregates, RMX, concrete masonry products and supplementary cementitious materials such as fly ash and slag. In WA, Adbri produces and supplies cement, slag and lime through its subsidiary, Cockburn Cement Limited. Adbri does not currently hold any assets or operate in markets for the supply of aggregates, RMX or asphalt in WA.
Release number
106/25
General enquiries
Submit an online enquiry
to ask a question or you can
make a report
to help us understand where there are problems.
Media enquiries
media@accc.gov.au or 1300 138 917. The media team is only able to answer requests and questions from journalists. Please only call this number if you are a journalist.</fullText>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <source>ACCC News</source>
    <title>Igneo's proposed acquisition of Benedict Recycling raises concerns</title>
    <link>https://www.accc.gov.au/media-release/igneos-proposed-acquisition-of-benedict-recycling-raises-concerns</link>
    <published>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 23:00:58 +0000</published>
    <fullText>Date
11 September 2025
Topics
Mergers and acquisitions
The ACCC has outlined its preliminary competition concerns with Igneo Infrastructure Partners’ proposed acquisition of Benedict Recycling Pty Ltd in a Statement of Issues today.
Igneo manages the infrastructure fund which owns Integrated Waste Services (IWS), which operates under the Recycle Central brand in the Newcastle region of NSW, supplying mixed building and demolition (B&amp;D) waste processing services. Benedict Recycling also provides these services in the Newcastle region.
The ACCC has preliminary concerns that the proposed acquisition is likely to substantially lessen competition in the supply of mixed B&amp;D processing services in the Newcastle region.
“We are concerned the proposed acquisition would lead to higher prices or reduced service quality for mixed B&amp;D waste processing in the Newcastle region,” ACCC Commissioner Dr Philip Williams said.
“IWS and Benedict Recycling are the largest waste processors in the region for mixed B&amp;D waste, and there are limited alternative waste processors for customers to choose from,” Dr Williams said. “IWS and Benedict Recycling are also each other’s closest competitors.”
The ACCC is continuing to investigate the extent to which landfills are competitive alternatives for customers using the mixed B&amp;D processing services offered by IWS and Benedict Recycling.
“Our preliminary view is that landfills are not an effective substitute for mixed B&amp;D processing,” Dr Williams said.
“Many waste collectors in the Newcastle region have a strong preference to deposit mixed B&amp;D waste at processors over landfill, reflecting reportedly higher costs of landfill disposal as well as other factors, including customer preferences for the recoverable material to be diverted from landfill, where possible, due to environmental considerations.”
As IWS operates a B&amp;D collections business in the Newcastle region, the ACCC is also considering the ability and incentive of IWS to disadvantage rival B&amp;D collection companies after the acquisition – for example, by increasing the prices it charges its collection rivals for mixed B&amp;D waste processing.
The ACCC invites submissions from interested parties in response to the Statement of Issues by 25 September 2025.
More information, including the Statement of Issues, can be found on the ACCC’s website at
Igneo Infrastructure Partners - Benedict Recycling Pty Ltd
.
Note to editors
B&amp;D waste is material generated from the demolition, construction or renovation of residential and commercial buildings, civil projects or infrastructure development. B&amp;D waste is non-putrescible (or ‘solid’), meaning it contains primarily non-organic materials that may or may not be recyclable.
Mixed B&amp;D waste is a subcategory of B&amp;D waste which involves materials that have not been segregated. Mixed B&amp;D waste may involve materials such as bricks, concrete, timber, glass, plastic, plasterboard, ceramics, metal, paper and cardboard.
Background
Igneo proposes to acquire 100 per cent of the shares of Benedict Recycling (the Proposed Acquisition).
Igneo is an unlisted infrastructure asset management business of the First Sentier Investors Group, an Australian asset manager with more than A$222 billion in funds under management (as at 30 June 2024). First Sentier Investors Group is ultimately owned by Mitsubishi UFJ Financial Group.
Igneo manages an infrastructure fund that owns IWS, a waste management business, with operations in Western Australia, South Australia, and the Newcastle/Hunter Valley region. IWS provides a range of waste management services including resource recovery, commercial composting, and disposal.
IWS owns Recycle Central Group (Recycle Central), a waste management business that provides waste collection, disposal and processing services for B&amp;D and commercial and industrial (C&amp;I) waste. Recycle Central operates two facilities in Greater Newcastle:
a large-scale waste processing facility, located in Kurri Kurri, 38 km from the Newcastle CBD; and
a waste transfer station located in Cardiff (in central Newcastle).
IWS offers collection services under several brands including ‘Central Skips’, through Recycle Central, and ‘Rent a skip’.
Benedict Recycling provides waste disposal and processing services for B&amp;D, C&amp;I, household and green waste across Greater Sydney (Chipping Norton, Unanderra, Smeaton Grange and Belrose), Bowral and Newcastle.
In Newcastle, Benedict Recycling operates a processing facility in Mayfield West, close to the centre of Newcastle (the Newcastle Recycling Centre).
Benedict Recycling does not operate a collections business.
Release number
105/25
General enquiries
Submit an online enquiry
to ask a question or you can
make a report
to help us understand where there are problems.
Media enquiries
media@accc.gov.au or 1300 138 917. The media team is only able to answer requests and questions from journalists. Please only call this number if you are a journalist.</fullText>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <source>ACCC News</source>
    <title>The Good Guys to pay $13.5m penalty for misleading store credit promotions</title>
    <link>https://www.accc.gov.au/media-release/the-good-guys-to-pay-135m-penalty-for-misleading-store-credit-promotions</link>
    <published>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 22:00:28 +0000</published>
    <fullText>Date
9 September 2025
Topics
Compliance and enforcement
The Federal Court has ordered The Good Guys Discount Warehouses (Australia) Pty Ltd to pay $13.5 million in penalties for misleading conduct in relation to several of its store credit and ‘StoreCash’ promotions, and for failing to provide store credit to more than 20,000 eligible consumers.
The proceedings related to 116 promotions run by The Good Guys between July 2019 and August 2023 in which it offered customers store credit (also called StoreCash in some promotions) if they spent a minimum amount, purchased a specific brand or product, or used a particular payment method. The amount of credit varied between $10 and $1,000, depending on the promotion.
The Good Guys admitted that its advertisements for the store credit promotions did not disclose, or adequately disclose, the expiry period of the store credit which, for the majority of promotions, was as short as 7 or 10 days, or, in most cases, that customers would only receive a store credit if they remained opted in to The Good Guys’ marketing communications.
“We took this court action because we were concerned that The Good Guys had failed to adequately disclose some really key conditions attached to these store credit promotions,” ACCC Chair Gina Cass-Gottlieb said.
“The chance to earn store credit may have encouraged some consumers to make a purchase at The Good Guys they otherwise may not have made or to choose this retailer over others. We were concerned some of those consumers may not have done so had they been aware of all the conditions.”
“When advertising promotional offers, all businesses must clearly disclose any key terms and conditions or limitations to avoid misleading consumers. Businesses that fail to do so could potentially face court proceedings and large penalties,” Ms Cass-Gottlieb said.
The Good Guys also admitted that it failed to provide about 21,500 consumers with store credit within the time frame it had specified.
“Businesses that use promotional programs to attract consumers and differentiate themselves from their competitors must ensure they provide any gifts or rebates to eligible consumers in the time period they said they would,” Ms Cass-Gottlieb said.
As well as the $13.5 million in penalties, the Court ordered The Good Guys to provide redress to certain consumers who participated in store credit promotions that did not disclose, or adequately disclose, the expiry period, by providing store credit with a longer expiry period. The Good Guys will contact consumers eligible for redress.
The Good Guys has already remediated consumers who did not receive their store credit due to not meeting the condition requiring them to remain opted in to marketing material, and the approximately 21,500 consumers who did not receive their credit within the specified time.
The Good Guys co-operated with the ACCC, admitted liability, and agreed to make joint submissions to the Court about orders, including in relation to penalties.
Consumer and fair trading concerns in the supermarket and retail sectors, with a focus on misleading pricing practices, are a current ACCC priority.
Note to editors
The Court accepted the parties’ joint submissions that part of the conduct contravened certain consumer protection provisions of the ASIC Act as the supply of store credit and StoreCash is a financial service. ASIC delegated its powers under the ASIC Act to certain senior officers of the ACCC to take this enforcement action.
The Court also found that The Good Guys contravened the Australian Consumer Law by failing to provide store credits to approximately 21,500 consumers within the time specified.
Example of store credit promotion:
Example of StoreCash promotion:
Background
The Good Guys is an Australian household appliance chain which conducts its business from physical stores across Australia as well as online. The Good Guys’ parent company is JB Hi-Fi Limited (ASX: JBH).
On 11 July 2024, the
ACCC instituted proceedings
against The Good Guys in the Federal Court.
Release number
104/25
General enquiries
Submit an online enquiry
to ask a question or you can
make a report
to help us understand where there are problems.
Media enquiries
media@accc.gov.au or 1300 138 917. The media team is only able to answer requests and questions from journalists. Please only call this number if you are a journalist.</fullText>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <source>ACCC News</source>
    <title>Fibre to the node trails all other NBN connection types for download speeds</title>
    <link>https://www.accc.gov.au/media-release/fibre-to-the-node-trails-all-other-nbn-connection-types-for-download-speeds</link>
    <published>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:20:00 +0000</published>
    <fullText>Date
4 September 2025
Topics
Telecommunications and internet
Households with a fibre to the node (FTTN) NBN connection are more likely to experience underperforming download speeds than any other fixed-line connection type, the ACCC’s
latest Measuring Broadband Australia report
has found.
FTTN connections with plan download speeds of 50 or 100 Mbps accounted for 86 per cent of all underperforming connections measured in the report during May 2025. Underperforming services very rarely, if ever, achieve at least 75 per cent of their plan download speed.
Nearly all of the underperforming FTTN connections measured in the report were also impaired. This means that the household cannot access their plan download speed because it exceeds the maximum attainable download speed that can be reached on their individual connection.
“We are concerned that there is a growing divide in the download speeds that Australians can access depending on their NBN connection type,” ACCC Commissioner Anna Brakey said.
“There remains a cohort of households with FTTN connections that rarely, if ever, achieve download speeds close to their plan’s download speed.”
The report found that FTTN connections with a plan download speed of 100 Mbps achieved an average download speed of 88.2 Mbps, compared to 104.4 Mbps on fibre to the premises (FTTP) connections and hybrid fibre coaxial (HFC) connections on the same plan.
Further, FTTN connections with a plan download speed of 50 Mbps achieved an average download speed of 47.6 Mbps, compared to 52.1 Mbps on FTTP connections and 52.3 Mbps on HFC connections.
However, the report found that FTTN connections with a plan download speed of 25 Mbps tend to deliver the plan speed, achieving an average download speed of 25.7 Mbps.
“Retailers must make customers aware if their NBN FTTN connection is not able to reach their chosen plan speed so that the customer can make an informed decision about which plan offers the best value for them,” Ms Brakey said.
Figure 1. Average download speed per plan and fixed-line access technology
NBN50
NBN100
The number of households with FTTN and fibre to the curb (FTTC) connections is declining as more households become eligible to upgrade their connection type. NBN is currently carrying out an upgrade program that will transition all FTTC connections and 95 per cent of households still on an FTTN connection to FTTP by 2030.
“We encourage consumers experiencing slow internet speeds or frequent outages on FTTN and FTTC connections to contact their broadband provider to see if they are eligible for a NBN connection upgrade, or what other options may be available,” Ms Brakey said.
Separately, the report found that HFC connections were the most prone to outages and were the most common connection type to record more than one outage per day on average.
Background
Data for the Measuring Broadband Australia program is provided by UK-based firm SamKnows using methodology based on speed testing programs delivered in the UK, US, Canada and New Zealand.
The report defines “Underperforming services” as those that reach above 75 per cent of plan speed in no more than 5 per cent of download tests. The report defines “Impaired services” as FTTN services where the maximum attainable download speed measured by NBN Co is below the plan download speed.
NBN services may exceed their maximum plan download speed due to overprovisioning. This is generally where NBN Co provides a slightly higher data rate than the wholesale plan download speed to accommodate for the portion of a connection’s data rate lost in retrieving information that enables a download to occur. NBN Co does not currently overprovision the uplink for NBN fixed-line connections.
Release number
103/25
General enquiries
Submit an online enquiry
to ask a question or you can
make a report
to help us understand where there are problems.
Media enquiries
media@accc.gov.au or 1300 138 917. The media team is only able to answer requests and questions from journalists. Please only call this number if you are a journalist.</fullText>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <source>ACCC News</source>
    <title>2025 Competition and Consumer Workshop: ACCC keynote address</title>
    <link>https://www.accc.gov.au/about-us/news/speeches/2025-competition-and-consumer-workshop-accc-keynote-address</link>
    <published>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</published>
    <fullText>On Thursday 4 September 2025, Ms Gina Cass-Gottlieb, ACCC Chair delivered the keynote address at the 2025 Competition and Consumer Workshop highlighting the role of right-sized regulation and the ACCC's impact in protecting consumers, promoting competition, and making markets work for all Australians.
Date
4 September 2025
Speakers
Ms Gina Cass-Gottlieb, Chair
Topics
Compliance and enforcement
Competition and exemptions
Mergers and acquisitions
Scams
Digital platforms and services
Energy
Food and groceries
Regulated infrastructure
Transcript
Introduction
Good morning, all. I begin by acknowledging the Traditional Custodians of lands, waterways and skies across Australia. I pay my respects to the Wurundjeri Woi-wurrung and Bunurong people, on whose country we meet today, and honour their culture and Elders, past and present. I also extend my respect to Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander colleagues who are here today.
It’s a pleasure to join you all today at this competition and consumer workshop. We meet at a time of profound disruption across our economy. Disruption that is reshaping markets, straining households and testing the resilience of businesses.
But this disruption is also creating opportunities for driving innovation and more competition and productivity. With the right guardrails in place, these forces of disruption can drive stronger competition, more choice, and better outcomes for consumers.
In today’s speech, I would like to explore how we are shaping those guardrails through the lens of right-sized regulation. That is, rules that are rigorous where harm is greatest, proportionate where burdens risk stifling progress, and always directed to the same end – protecting consumers, promoting competition, and enabling innovation and productivity.
First, the reforms underway to ensure our regulatory frameworks are fit for purpose.
Second, how we enforce competition law using the tools at our disposal to achieve the best outcomes for consumers.
Third, how we protect consumer trust and wellbeing through robust consumer law enforcement.
Finally, how we steward essential and emerging markets for the future, including the energy transition.
Taken together, these roles – reform, enforcement, protection and stewardship – reflect the ACCC’s impact. Our purpose is clear: to protect consumers, to promote competition, and to make markets work for all Australians.
Enduring principles for an uncertain future
To begin, I will briefly set the stage of our current economic context and the principles that guide our work.
The challenges we face today are often described as unprecedented. Unprecedented is shorthand to describe digital disruption, the impact of climate change, geopolitical uncertainty and cost-of-living pressures.
But while these forces may be new in scale and speed, the path through them is not necessarily unknowable. And Australia has faced profound economic change before.
History tells us that well-designed competition and consumer policy can be transformative in moments like this.
The 1995 National Competition Policy reforms, inspired by the Hilmer Report, are often described as critical components of the significant microeconomic reforms of that decade. They embedded nationally consistent competition rules, initiated removal of legislative barriers to competition across the federation, extended the Act’s reach across public and private enterprise, and enshrined the welfare objective clause that still guides our work.
With the benefits of a series of amendments the
Competition and Consumer Act 2010
– with its simple, powerful objective of enhancing the welfare of Australians – remains our compass. And when I think about how best to apply this landmark legislation, I often return to the work of the late Professor Maureen Brunt.
Professor Brunt was ahead of her time. She recognised that competition law is not just about markets, it’s about people, and about ensuring the competitive process works for their greater benefit. In her writings she urges regulators to “keep our eyes on the ultimate objective, namely the protection of the consumer by means of an efficient competitive process”.
This insight is as relevant now as it was when she first wrote it. Because as our economy transitions – through decarbonisation, technological change, and global uncertainty – the process of competition is more important than ever. It is what drives investment, spurs innovation, and builds economic resilience.
Reform: right-sized regulation for today’s challenges
Now, to the first of my points today: reform to ensure our regulatory settings remain fit for purpose.
The ACCC is committed to a right-size, risk-based regulatory approach. One that protects consumer wellbeing and competition, while fostering economic dynamism and productivity.
Merger reform
We see this principle in action with merger reform. When the Treasurer introduced the merger reforms into Australian Parliament late last year, he described them as a big step towards boosting competition and productivity.
These reforms seek to strike the right balance between seeing and preventing anti-competitive acquisitions, while allowing those that are unlikely to raise competition issues to proceed promptly and with certainty. And importantly, the design of the new regime and the ACCC’s committed approach to delivery of the new regime, has focused on regulatory timeliness, predictability and proportionality – with clear processes for engaging with businesses and consumers.
The journey started here, at this very LCA workshop 4 years ago, when Rod Sims sparked a debate about whether our merger control regime in Australia was fit for purpose. A lot has happened in the short period since.
The last 18 months have been fast-moving. Treasury’s decision to allow for voluntary notifications from 1 July this year prompted significant preparatory work within a compressed timeframe. Suffice it to say, our teams have been working hard, not only to ready the agency, but to help business and advisers prepare. It is obvious that an enormous amount of work is also being done by many of you here today to ready your clients for this change.
Already we are seeing the regime take shape. Our consultation on merger process and assessment guidelines has led to updated guidance and more will follow. Our email alerts, now with more than 700 subscribers, have provided timely, rolling updates to questions and issues as they arise. And later this month, we will begin regular two-way engagement sessions to understand the lived experiences of businesses, advisers and the ACCC of interacting with the new regime.
While the voluntary period has started quietly, with just two notifications received so far, we expect this to change as we move closer to 1 January. And we’re pleased to note that the first voluntary notification we received was completed and approved in the earliest timeframe possible on business day 15.
Our focus is on administering the regime transparently and efficiently – calibrating our processes so the burden on business is proportionate to risk while ensuring that we are able to do the important job of preventing anti-competitive mergers.
The ACCC shares a common interest with business that the process is flexible and efficient. A critical feature here is the pre-notification engagement.
We understand that parties may want to discuss a transaction before they are ready to provide a draft notification and our team is available for these discussions. However, in most cases, we will need to receive a draft notification for our team to have a meaningful pre-engagement discussion.
A draft notification allows our team to better identify whether any additional information should be provided when you notify, or which questions answered, based on the circumstances relating to that particular acquisition.
I would like to reinforce the importance of this engagement with our team. Simply not answering a question on the form, or saying it’s not relevant, will slow the process down and potentially expose the notification to later being found to be materially incomplete.
Done well, prenotification helps businesses and the ACCC clarify what information is needed upfront, reduces delays, and minimises the risk of notifications being found incomplete. And we are pleased to see business and advisers taking up this option.
Similarly, the waiver process will allow non-contentious acquisitions to proceed with minimal regulatory burden, while ensuring our scrutiny remains rigorous where it matters most.
We are committed to learning and refining as we go. Transparency is built into the system through regular reporting and scheduled reviews at 12 months and three years.
The voluntary transition period we are in now allows the ACCC, business and advisers to test and refine approaches before mandatory notification and the other features come into full effect. We expect it will take some time for the new regime to feel ‘routine’. However, we know that mandatory merger regimes based on notification thresholds operate successfully in many other jurisdictions, and we are confident in replicating that success here. What matters is that Australia now has a merger regime that is fit for the challenges ahead, one that protects competition while enabling investment, innovation and growth.
The same principle of risk based proportionality extends to digital platforms and other concentrated markets.
Digital platforms
At a time of profound and unprecedented digital transformation and disruption, where the vast majority of economic activity now occurs in the digital sphere, right sized, effective regulatory frameworks are essential to maintain vibrant competition and protect consumers from harm.
In the ACCC’s tenth and final report for the Digital Platform Services Inquiry, we found that without sufficient laws in place, Australian consumers and businesses are continuing to encounter a significant number of harmful practices across a range of digital platform services. It is our view that a proactive approach to the regulation of digital platforms is needed and the ACCC continues to advocate for a new digital competition regime, targeted to the few platforms and critical intermediary services that exhibit market power and impede competition and diversified innovation.
The proposed digital competition regime is based on service-specific codes of conduct. These codes would be tailored to account for the particular characteristics and competitive dynamics of each service, and updated in response to changes in technology and business models, in ways that promote pro-competitive and consumer-friendly innovation.
Scams prevention
We are also seeing strong, proportionate and proactive regulation more broadly. The
Scams Prevention Framework Bill 2025 –
world-first legislation to enhance scam protections across the economy – was legislated this year. This reform sets consistent obligations that build on positive progress by the National Anti-Scam Centre, government and industry to disrupt scams: scam losses in Australia fell by more than 25 per cent to $2 billion in 2024.
Supermarket and retail
And in the supermarket and retail sector, the now mandatory Food and Grocery Code came into effect in April 2025, imposing civil penalties on large grocery businesses for noncompliance. And the Government has also provided $30 million in dedicated funding to support the ACCC’s enforcement and investigations.
Across mergers, digital platforms, scams and supermarkets, the principle is the same: regulation that is fit for purpose, proportionate in design and implementation, and directed at the greatest harms to business, the economy and consumers.
Regulatory reform and advocacy are critical to ensuring our frameworks remain fit for purpose. But equally important is what we do here and now – using the laws and tools already at our disposal to protect competition and consumers.
Competition enforcement for the benefit of consumers and the economy
Which leads me to my second point for today: how we enforce competition law using the tools at our disposal to achieve the best outcomes for consumers.
When businesses compete to meet consumer needs, they are incentivised to innovate and improve – to offer greater choice, lower prices and better-quality products and services.
Workably competitive markets ensure consumers are better off and the economy grows efficiently. When competition works, Australians benefit twice through lower prices and better services today and innovation that drives prosperity into the future.
This is the very basis of the ACCC’s mandate as the Commonwealth’s competition and consumer protection regulator: improving economic efficiency and productivity. By promoting competition in markets, we promote the production of the most highly valued goods and services at the optimum quality and the lowest possible price for the benefit of Australian consumers.
And we use every tool available – from compliance engagement and education to enforceable undertakings and of course, our sharpest tool, litigation – to address conduct that harms consumers or the competitive process.
Our recent action against Google demonstrates in practice our ability to combine enforcement tools to achieve an outcome that most benefits competition and consumers in a timely way.
Google admitted to breaching Australia’s competition laws in relation to understandings it reached in the past with each of Telstra and Optus for pre-installation and placement of Google Search on Android devices and agreed to jointly submit to the court that it should pay a penalty of $55 million. Importantly, this outcome is coupled with a court-enforceable undertaking containing forward-looking commitments to modify the way it distributes Google Search in Australia. It also builds on previous undertakings provided by each of Telstra, Optus and TPG.
Google’s commitments – including removing certain pre-installation and default search engine restrictions on Android devices and providing for the untying of Google Play from Search and Chrome – will deliver meaningful benefits. They will provide for immediate and meaningful change for millions of Australian consumers and allow competitors of Google to be able to compete on their merits.
The timing here matters. AI search tools are revolutionising how we search for information. It is vital that competitors in this space can gain meaningful exposure to Australian consumers.
I am pleased that Google has cooperated with us in putting forward a resolution to the Court and offering an undertaking, avoiding the need for what would have undoubtedly been protracted and costly contested litigation. Of course, it will be a matter for the court to determine appropriate orders, including penalty, and we hope the matter will be heard before the end of the year.
Protecting competition is also at the heart of our action against cartel conduct. Last week, the Full Federal Court dismissed appeals in two major cartel cases. The court upheld penalties of $1.5 million against Delta Building Automation and $120,000 against its director for trying to rig a taxpayer-funded tender. It also confirmed record penalties of $57.5 million against BlueScope Steel and $500,000 against its former executive for attempts to fix the prices of flat steel products. The message from the court is clear: even the attempt
to form a cartel is illegal, and the consequences are severe.
Following these outcomes, this week we announced two new cartel proceedings: one alleging price fixing in the supply of fresh produce to ALDI. Another involving major suppliers of mobile crane services in Sydney. These cases cut to the core of markets that matter to Australians – our food supply chains and the construction and infrastructure sectors that underpin our economy.
Beyond these cases, we continue to pursue other major matters before the courts, including our misuse of power case against Mastercard and our cartel case against Spotless and Ventia.
Taken together, these proceedings illustrate the complexity and longevity of contested competition litigation. But they also show our resolve to take action where it is warranted. With the cases the ACCC has before the Court spanning allegations of misuse of market power, anti-competitive conduct and cartel conduct, it is proving to be a notable time for competition enforcement in Australia.
Consumer enforcement: protecting wellbeing and trust
Workably competitive markets are vital – but competition alone is not enough. Consumers also need trust and confidence: trust in the businesses they engage with and confidence that strong protections are in place if things go wrong.
And I will now move to the third theme of this speech: how we protect consumer trust and wellbeing through robust consumer law enforcement.
Consumer law provides the critical foundations. In an era where disruption is constant, trust has never mattered more. When trust collapses, so too does the confidence to engage in markets, to spend, and to trial new services and new technologies.
Trust underpins the social contract that ensures markets function and economies flourish. It matters to all of us in this room, as regulators, advisers, and stewards of the systems and institutions that influence people’s lives.
Our consumer protection role is complementary to our competition role. Together they promote confidence and ensure consumer dollars are not devalued by misleading conduct and that fair dealing businesses do not suffer disadvantage from deceptive business practices. Just as with our competition enforcement, we use all the tools available to us to protect Australians from unsafe products, misleading conduct and harmful business practices.
Our focus is on conduct that results in significant harm. And our priority is always to manage risk proportionately and achieve the best possible outcome for the community.
This year, for example, we instituted proceedings in the Federal Court against Bupa. The company admitted to engaging in misleading conduct and making false or misleading representations, by advising members they were not entitled to private health insurance benefits for their entire claim. It also admitted to engaging in unconscionable conduct. The ACCC and Bupa will jointly ask the Federal Court to impose a total penalty of $35 million. And it will be a matter for the Court to determine whether the penalty and other orders sought are appropriate.
Another example of enforcement action we have taken to address consumer harm is the proceedings we instituted last year against Optus Mobile for engaging in unconscionable conduct when selling telecommunications goods and services to hundreds of consumers, many of whom were vulnerable or experiencing disadvantage. Optus admitted to engaging in unconscionable conduct, and the ACCC and Optus will jointly ask the Federal Court to impose a total penalty of $100 million. Again, it is a matter for the Court to determine whether the penalty and other orders sought are appropriate.
However, litigation is not the only means by which we achieve compliance. For example, last year our sweep of Black Friday and post-Christmas sales revealed widespread misrepresentations – such as ‘site wide’ discounts that were not, in fact, site wide. We publicised our findings, issued infringement notices, and engaged with businesses to improve their practices. The full range of tools enables the ACCC to choose enforcement actions proportionate to harm, risk and the seriousness of the conduct.
Each of these actions – whether through litigation, compliance sweeps, infringement notices, or direct engagement – serves the same purpose: to protect consumers, to build trust, and to strengthen the proper functioning of markets. Together with our competition mandate, our fair trading and consumer protection and product safety work ensures Australians can participate in commercial life with confidence, knowing the guardrails are in place to deter harm.
Stewardship: making markets work
Consumer trust also depends on the way our markets work over time. Which brings me to my final point for today, the role of the ACCC in infrastructure regulation and market monitoring to deliver lasting change that improves the everyday lives of Australians.
Over the past year, we have worked to improve transparency in national telecommunications infrastructure. A significant step in this direction was the introduction of a new NBN Co record-keeping rule, giving the public clear information about network performance and service quality.
We also monitor sectors of critical national infrastructure where competition is limited, or services are essential. Through regular reports, we shine a light on market dynamics, promote efficiency, and inform investment and consumption choices.
Our stewardship is forward-looking. The ACCC’s purpose is to make markets work for all Australians – now and in the future.
That future is being shaped by the energy transition. And while the ACCC is not an environmental regulator, our work touches on critical parts of the net zero transition – from environmental collaborations to infrastructure monopolies, mergers, and new markets. Our role as regulator is not to stand in the way, but to stand guard: to weigh benefits and detriments carefully, protecting consumers and the competitive process without stifling innovation.
As economies transition to net zero, competitive markets are vital to ensure that resources are allocated efficiently, innovation is incentivised, and the costs of change are mitigated. Competition pressures companies to differentiate, to reduce waste and cut costs, and to deliver better value. It is the engine of dynamism and productivity – features that, when paired with effective and proportionate regulation, can support a strong economy and a successful transition to net zero.
We also recognise the paradox of rapid transformation. At times, government support, regulation and collaboration will be needed to enable the creation of new, low carbon technology and industries. But wherever possible, we must preserve the conditions that enable workable competition to be present and be maintained.
Many sustainability collaborations will not harm competition. Where there is the potential for harm, there may also be public benefits outweighing that harm. Competition law can accommodate these collaborations through authorisations.
The long-term vision that underpins the ACCC’s approach to sustainability are markets governed by truth, substantiation and transparency which enable competition on the merits for businesses investing in genuine sustainability.
Conclusion
Across everything we do at the ACCC, we remain conscious that competition regulation and consumer protection must serve as a deliberate and effective guardrail. To this end, our focus is on right-sized regulation: balancing the interests of consumers, businesses and the wider economy.
We approach this work with transparency and proportionality, including through deep engagement with regulatory peers at home and abroad, all levels of government, the business community, and consumer representatives.
And we will continue, as always, to remain committed to our purpose to enhance competition across our economy, to promote the welfare of consumers and small businesses, and to make markets work for all Australians. As Professor Maureen Brunt urged, we keep our eyes on the ultimate objective: consumers better off through an efficient competitive process.
Thank you.</fullText>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <source>ACCC News</source>
    <title>IAG's proposed acquisition of WA's RAC insurance business raises concerns</title>
    <link>https://www.accc.gov.au/media-release/iags-proposed-acquisition-of-was-rac-insurance-business-raises-concerns</link>
    <published>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 23:20:19 +0000</published>
    <fullText>Date
4 September 2025
Topics
Mergers and acquisitions
Insurance
The ACCC has outlined its preliminary competition concerns with Insurance Australia Group Limited’s (ASX: IAG) proposed acquisition of RAC Insurance Pty Limited (RACI) from
the Royal Automobile Club of Western Australia
Inc in a Statement of Issues published today.
IAG and RACI both supply motor insurance and home and contents insurance in Western Australia. The proposed acquisition would result in IAG underwriting motor insurance and home and contents insurance under the RAC brand.
The ACCC’s preliminary view is that the proposed acquisition is likely to have the effect of substantially lessening competition in both the supply of motor insurance and the supply of home and contents insurance in Western Australia.
“RACI is the leading provider of both motor and home and contents insurance in Western Australia and has a significantly larger market share in each compared to any other insurer,” ACCC Commissioner Dr Philip Williams said.
“RACI competes strongly in Western Australia with its well-recognised brand and focus on customer service. It also appears likely to continue to compete strongly in the future, if the proposed acquisition does not eventuate.”
“We are concerned that the acquisition would increase concentration in an already highly concentrated market,” Dr Williams said.
The ACCC is concerned that the reduction in competition may enable IAG to increase premiums and reduce the quality of its own and RACI’s motor insurance and home and contents insurance products in the future.
The ACCC is also concerned that the proposed acquisition may enable IAG to limit rival insurers’ access to quality and cost-effective repairers in Western Australia or increase rivals’ costs of acquiring repair services in the state.
Accessing repair services, such as smash repairs, windscreen repairs and home repairs, is a key aspect of providing insurance, and restricting access to such services would likely reduce the competitiveness of rival insurers in Western Australia.
The ACCC invites submissions in response to the Statement of Issues by 18 September 2025. Parties can contact the ACCC via
mergers@accc.gov.au
.
More information including the Statement of Issues is available on the ACCC’s public register here:
IAG Limited – RAC Insurance Pty Limited | ACCC
.
Background
IAG is an ASX-listed (ASX: IAG) general insurance company operating in Australia and New Zealand. IAG provides a range of personal and commercial insurance products in Australia directly under its owned brands, including NRMA, Swann Insurance, ROLLiN’, Cylo and Lumley Special Vehicles. Through its joint venture business, Insurance Manufacturers of Australia Pty Limited, IAG provides personal lines insurance in Victoria distributed by its joint venture partner RACV.
In addition, IAG provides intermediated insurance through brokers, authorised financial representatives, institutions and agents under the CGU and WFI brands. IAG also underwrites insurance products distributed by financial institutions, including Bendigo and Adelaide Bank, People’s Choice Bank and, since 2023, ANZ Bank.
The Royal Automobile Club of Western Australia (RAC) is a Western Australian based member-owned mutual association that provides roadside assistance, general insurance products, and other ancillary services to its members. RACI underwrites motor insurance and home and contents insurance for RAC.
RAC distributes other personal lines of general insurance underwritten by third party insurers. Namely, RAC distributes travel insurance underwritten by Tokio Marine &amp; Nichido Fire Insurance Co. Ltd. RAC also has arrangements in place for the supply of health insurance underwritten by HCF, life insurance underwritten by NobleOak Life Limited and pet insurance underwritten by RACQ Insurance (RACQI).
The Proposed Acquisition does not involve the acquisition by IAG of RAC's roadside assistance business or its other operations including RAC's auto servicing and repair services, finance, retirement living, home security, batteries, tyres, travel and tourism operations.
Release number
102/25
General enquiries
Submit an online enquiry
to ask a question or you can
make a report
to help us understand where there are problems.
Media enquiries
media@accc.gov.au or 1300 138 917. The media team is only able to answer requests and questions from journalists. Please only call this number if you are a journalist.</fullText>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <source>ACCC News</source>
    <title>Four mobile crane companies in court over alleged cartel activity</title>
    <link>https://www.accc.gov.au/media-release/four-mobile-crane-companies-in-court-over-alleged-cartel-activity</link>
    <published>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:12:57 +0000</published>
    <fullText>Date
3 September 2025
Topics
Compliance and enforcement
The ACCC has commenced civil cartel proceedings in the Federal Court against four mobile crane hire companies – Borger Crane Hire &amp; Rigging Services Pty Ltd, MCR Melrose Pty Ltd, Two Way Cranes Pty Ltd and Ultra-Lift Cranes Pty Ltd – and four senior executives, for allegedly arranging not to supply services to certain customers or sites. Two of the companies also allegedly attempted to fix prices.
The ACCC alleges the four Sydney-based companies breached Australia’s cartel laws and likely impacted customers and sites, including major construction sites, on a number of occasions between 2020 and 2024.
“The allegations in this case involve the conduct of the largest mobile crane companies in Sydney that regularly supply mobile cranes for major infrastructure projects, small business and residential building work,” ACCC Chair Gina Cass-Gottlieb said.
“When companies collude to limit supply or fix prices, it reduces competition in the market and harms businesses and consumers.”
The ACCC alleges the four companies used WhatsApp to identify certain building sites or customers and make arrangements between themselves that some or all of these companies would not supply cranes to these sites or customers.
Borger Cranes’ General Manager Shawn Borger, Melrose Cranes’ former Managing Director Gregg Melrose and former General Manager Ryan Melrose, and the Managing Director of both Two Way Cranes and Ultra-Lift Cranes Frank Zammit are alleged to be involved in this conduct.
It is alleged that the senior executives coordinated their actions using WhatsApp chat groups named the “Crane Companies” and “Big 3”.
The ACCC alleges that Melrose Cranes and Gregg Melrose made three attempts in 2022 to fix mobile crane hire rates with competing crane companies.
It is also alleged that in 2022 Borger Cranes and Shawn Borger attempted to fix cross-hire rates, which are the rates that apply when a mobile crane company rents a crane from a competitor crane company.
“
Mobile cranes are used across a range of critical sectors of the Australian economy, including construction, infrastructure, utilities, and mining, so ensuring businesses compete vigorously to supply services into these sectors is extremely important,” Ms Cass-Gottlieb said.
“We will continue to hold companies and individuals accountable for conduct that we consider harms competition and, ultimately, the broader community.”
The ACCC is seeking declarations, pecuniary penalties and costs against the businesses and the four senior executives, disqualification orders against three of the senior executives, and compliance orders against Borger Cranes, Two Way Cranes and Ultra-Lift Cranes.
Background
Mobile cranes are self-powered cranes that can move on their own. They include wheeled or truck-mounted cranes that can drive on roads. They come in various sizes and lifting capacities.
The alleged conduct would have impacted building and infrastructure projects across the Sydney area from 2020 to 2024. Mobile crane hire is important to the Australian economy, including in construction (from large scale government-funded construction projects to small scale residential projects), infrastructure, utilities, and mining.
Some of the alleged conduct arose in the context of ongoing negotiations between the mobile crane hire companies and the CFMEU regarding new Enterprise Bargaining Agreements. Certain alleged arrangements were entered into in circumstances where mobile crane companies had been, or were at risk of being, removed from sites due to the CFMEU. Other alleged arrangements were entered into in circumstances where the affected customers were identified as having unpaid debts for mobile crane hire services.
Note to editors
A cartel exists when businesses agree to act together instead of competing with each other. Cartel conduct can include price fixing, sharing markets, rigging bids and controlling output (limiting the amount or type of goods and services available).
More information about cartel conduct can be found on the
ACCC’s website
.
Anyone who thinks they may have been involved in cartel conduct is urged to call the ACCC Cartel Immunity Hotline on (02) 9230 3894. More information about the immunity process is available on the
ACCC’s website
. People can also report alleged cartel conduct by using the
anonymous cartel portal
.
Public procurement officials who want to know more about detecting cartels are encouraged to contact the ACCC Cartel Outreach team at
carteloutreach@accc.gov.au
.
The ACCC investigates cartel conduct and can take civil cartel proceedings in the Federal Court or refer serious cartel conduct to the Commonwealth Director of Public Prosecutions.
For corporations, the maximum civil penalty which may be ordered by a Court for cartel conduct which occurred before 9 November 2022 is the greater of:
$10 million,
if the Court can determine the value of the benefits reasonably attributable to the act or omission – three times that value, or
if the Court cannot determine the value of the benefits reasonably attributable to the act or omission – 10 per cent of the corporation’s annual turnover in the 12 months preceding the act or omission.
An individual found to have been involved in civil cartel conduct before 9 November 2022 is subject to a maximum penalty of $500,000 for each act or omission.
The maximum civil penalties for cartel conduct by corporations and individuals were substantially increased with effect from 9 November 2022. The maximum penalty for individuals after 9 November 2022 is $2.5 million for each act or omission. For corporations, the maximum penalty after 9 November 2022 is the greater of:
$50 million,
if the Court can determine the value of the benefits reasonably attributable to the act or omission – three times that value, or
if the court cannot determine the value of the benefits reasonably attributable to the act or omission – 30% of the company’s adjusted turnover during the breach turnover period.
Release number
101/25
General enquiries
Submit an online enquiry
to ask a question or you can
make a report
to help us understand where there are problems.
Media enquiries
media@accc.gov.au or 1300 138 917. The media team is only able to answer requests and questions from journalists. Please only call this number if you are a journalist.</fullText>
  </entry>
</feed>
